Guide to the Holly Pruett papers 1969-2004
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Holly Pruett papers
1969-2004
1991-2004
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Coll 679
Pruett, Holly
4.4 cubic feet 10 document cases and 1 flat box
Papers relating to Holly Pruett's work in gay rights activism, particularly with the 1994 No on 13 campaign.
Measure 13 was a ballot measure placed on the ballot for the 1994 November election in Oregon. The measure, written by the right-wing group Oregon Citizens Alliance (OCA), called for the state constitution to be amended so that homosexuals were denied “minority status” protections, and so that public schools and other organizations would be barred from “promoting or expressing approval of homosexuality.” The measure was remarkably similar to 1992’s Measure 9, which had also been authored by the Oregon Citizens Alliance and been defeated at the polls. Thanks to a vigorous opposition campaign, Measure 13 also failed at the polls, with 52% of voters rejecting the measure. In the aftermath of the 1994 election, staffers from the No on 13 campaign formed the gay rights advocacy group Basic Rights Oregon.
Measure 36 was a 2004 Oregon initiative which sought to amend the state constitution so as to explicitly define marriage as being between one man and one woman. Basic Rights Oregon led the campaign opposing the measure. However, the measure ultimately passed, 56.63% to 43.37%, and the Oregon Constitution was amended so as to officially bar legal recognition of same-sex marriages. In May 2014, United States District Judge Michael McShane ruled that the clause prohibiting same-sex marriage was unconstitutional, as it violated the Equal Protection Clause of the United States Constitution’s 14th Amendment. Since then, Oregon has legally recognized same-sex marriages.
The collection primarily consists of papers relating to Holly Pruett’s activism regarding gay rights in Oregon. The bulk of the collection consists of records from the No on 13 campaign of 1994, wherein Pruett served as deputy campaign manager, but records from the 2004 No on 36 campaign, records from Support Our Communities Political Action Committee (SOC PAC), and early records of Basic Rights Oregon are also present. Another major component of the collection concerns a report which Pruett co-authored with No on 13 campaign manager Julie Davis, titled, “Oregon’s No on 13 Campaign: A Case Study in Movement Building through Electoral Organizing.” Additional materials include Pruett’s Master’s thesis, papers relating to Pruett's involvement with other activism-related activities, papers relating to non-Oregon gay rights issues in the early 1990s, a 1969 brochure for Black Studies at Reed College, and issues of gay and lesbian-oriented publications.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: No on 13 campaign
Series B: Basic Rights Oregon
Series C: Support Our Communities Political Action Committee (SOC PAC)
Series D: Writings
Series E: No on 36 campaign
Series F: Other activism
Series G: Other papers and ephemera
The collection is open to the public.
Lib. Acc. 28925
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Pruett, Holly--Archives; Davis, Julie
Basic Rights Oregon; Support Our Communities Political Action Committee; Oregon Citizens Alliance
Oregon--Gay rights
Gay rights--Oregon; Political campaigns--Oregon; Referendum--Oregon; Social action--Oregon; Homophobia--Oregon
Gays and Lesbians; Political Campaigns; Oregon
Correspondence; Reports; Administrative records; Financial records; Clippings (information artifacts); Publications (documents); Masters theses; Fliers (printed matter)
Just Out
- No on 13 campaign, 1992-1994; 1994; Series A
  - Original folders, Subseries 1
    Materials organized and titled identically to Pruett's original order. Unless stated otherwise, the folder title accurately reflects its contents.
    - Active field - PDX, 1994 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Active field - State, 1994 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Cable show, 1994 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Business endorsements, 1994 (Box-folder 1/4)
      Handwritten notes.
    - Coalition planning, 1994 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Communications plan, 1994 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Communications team, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1/7)
      Includes materials relating to the 1992 No on 9 campaign
    - Field, 1994 (Box-folder 1/8)
      Contains various papers, including ones relating to campaign field offices, from which the folder's title was likely derived.
    - Internal/Personnel, 1994 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - July 8th materials, 1994 (Box-folder 1/10)
      Title refers to date when signatures to put Measure 13 on the ballot were submitted.
    - Lit pieces, 1994 (Box-folder 1/11)
      Includes some campaign literature for John Kitzhaber's gubenatorial run.
    - Misc. communications, 1994 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Old 'To Do' lists, 1994 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - POC plan, 1994 (Box-folder 1/14)
      Materials regarding outreach to African Americans.
    - Persuasion literature, 1994 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - State/local protocols, 1994 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Voters Pamphlet, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2/2)
      Includes statements of opposition to 1992's Measure 9.
  - Item values for benefit auction, 1994 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Benefit auction program, 1994 October 7 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Bigot Busters materials, 1994 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Board endorsements, 1994 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Campaign calendar, 1994 August-November (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Campaign planning records, 1994 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Campaign security and emergency communications, 1994 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Committee minutes, 1994 August (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Committee roster, 1994 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Correspondence, Subseries 2
    - Correspondence and memos, 1994 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Fax correspondence, 1994 August-October (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Fax cover sheets, 1994 August-September (Box-folder 2/14)
      Contents of faxes were missing or misplaced by time of processing.
    - Lawn signs, 1994 September (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Non-Profit Support Services, 1994 October (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Materials re David Allen case and "Five Oaks Incident", 1994 (Box-folder 2/17)
    Criminal case and controversy which supporters of Measure 13 used as a campaign issue.
  - Correspondence and forms re endorsements, 1994 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Flyers, 1994 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Even flyers, 1994 September-October (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Flyers and publications forwarded to Pruett, 1994 (Box-folder 2/21)
    Materials had been clipped together.
  - Finances and fundraising, Subseries 3
    - Financial records, 1994 (Box-folder 2/22)
      Includes some financial records for Support Our Communities Politican Action Committee (SOC PAC).
    - Fundraising flyers, 1994 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Fundraising records, 1994 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - "Initative Efforts in 1994, with Preliminary Dollars", 1994 November 30 (Box-folder 3/3)
      Sheet erronously has correction implying that Measure 13 passed. Additional copy attached to records in another folder indicate that the person correcting the sheet meant to mark the measure listed below.
    - List of No on 9 donors, and attached fundraising letter to Joe Brown, 1994 August-September (Box-folder 3/4)
      List most likely compiled to determine who to contact for fundraising for the No on 13 campaign.
  - Lists and contact information, Subseries 4
    - Rosters and contact information, 1994 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - List of cable access shows in Oregon and in Vancouver, Washington, 1994 September (Box-folder 3/6)
    - List and contact information of attendees at conference in Portland, "Lon and Beyond", circa 1994 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Contact information for local branches of "friendly" state-wide organizations, 1994 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Lists and contact information of human dignity groups, 1994 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Coos and Clatsop County contacts, 1994 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Lane County contacts, 1994 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - List of organizations opposing Measure 13, 1994 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - List and contact information of attendees at SOC PAC conference, 1993 December - 1994 March (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Messaging, media and publications, Subseries 5
    - Corvallis Gazette-Times article, 1994 September 9 (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Papers and correspondence re messaging, 1994 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Research on messaging, "13 is the same as 9", 1994 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - "It's B-A-A-CK" message drafts, 1994 August (Box-folder 3/16)
    - League of Women Voter's Guide, 1994 November (Box-folder 12/2)
    - No on 13 mailer, 1994 (Box-folder 3/17)
    - MOBA Media Inc. news releases, 1994 September - October (Box-folder 3/18)
    - "Morning Message/Message of the Day" releases, 1994 September-November (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Newsletters and mailings from allied organizations, 1994 (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Newspaper articles and news reports, 1994 (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Newspaper articles and promotional materials, 1994 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Oregonian piece on Measure 9, 1992 (Box-folder 4/2)
      Used for research during the No on 13 campaign.
    - Photocopied newspaper clippings, 1994 (Box-folder 3/22-3/23)
      Also includes articles about other gay rights-related news that year.
    - Photocopied newspaper clippings sent to Timothy Lehman, 1994 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Quotes from Barbara Bernstein interviews, 1994 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Issue of Wall Street Journal, 1994 October 7 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Opposition research materials, Subseries 6
    - Writing on anti-Mormonism of Measure 13 authors, 1994 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Materials re Oregon Citizens Alliance (OCA) and allied organizations, 1994 (Box-folder 4/6-4/8)
      Group that authored and lobbied for Measure 13.
    - Yes on 13 newspaper mailings, 1994 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - No on 13 rally records, 1994 September-October (Box-folder 4/10)
  - No on 13 rally photograph, 1994 October 9 (Box-folder 4/11)
    Thank you note to Julie Davis is written on the back.
  - Religious Right Response materials, 1994 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Sheet music, "Take One Step" by Alice Knotte, 1994 (Box-folder 4/13)
    Includes a letter from Knotte about the song.
  - Papers and correspondence re staff and volunteers, 1994 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Staffing - blank personal profile form, 1994 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Staff weekly reports, 1994 August-September (Box-folder 4/16)
  - Statements, Subseries 7
    - No on 13 statements, 1994 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Yes on 13 statements, 1994 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Statements, mailings, etc., 1994 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Statements by organizations, 1994 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Text of Measure 13, 1994 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Voter Contact Services cross count profile summary, 1994 September (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Voters' Pamphlet statements against Measure 9, 1992 (Box-folder 12/9)
    Presumably used for research during the No on 13 campaign.
  - Write-up on anti-gay discrimination against Marge Montague, 1994 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Post-election activities, Subseries 8
    - Records, 1994 November (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Debrief meetings, 1994 November (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Easel sheets with notes from debrief meetings, 1994 November (Box-folder 12/5)
    - Plans, 1994 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Staff assessments of campaign, 1994 November-December (Box-folder 5/6)
- Basic Rights Oregon, 1995; Series B
  Organization that grew out of the No on 13 campaign.
  - (Box-folder 5/7)
  - (Box-folder 12/6)
  - (Box-folder 5/8)
- Support Our Communities Political Action Committee (SOC PAC), 1993-1995; Series C
  Some additional SOC PAC materials located in Series A: No on 13 campaign
  - Records, 1993 (Box-folder 5/9)
    Removed from binder.
  - Records, 1993 (Box-folder 5/10)
    Loose records.
  - Records, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Records, 1995 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Campaign planning and literature, 1993 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - List of endorsers, 1994 January (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Job and position descriptions, 1994 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Mailings, 1993 December - 1994 July (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Materials for opposition to Oregon Citizens Alliance municipal measures, 1993 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - "Reading", 1993; undated (Box-folder 7/8)
    Articles, notes, and SOC PAC records that had been housed together.
  - Steering committee records, 1994 August-September (Box-folder 7/9)
- Writings, 1992-1995; Series D
  Papers written by Pruett and Julie Davis, and related materials.
  - Master's thesis, "Fighting the Good Fight: Leadership Development in a Political Action Committee", 1994 May (Box-folder 7/10)
  - SOC PAC papers found with master's thesis, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 7/11)
  - No on 13 campaign report, Subseries 1
    Report co-authored with Julie Davis through Basic Rights Oregon, titled, "Oregon's No on 13 Campaign: A Case Study in Movement Building through Electorial Organizing."
    - Proposal for report, 1995 January 20 (Box-folder 7/12)
      Proposal titles the report as, "Out-Organizing the Radical Right: Organizational Development and Campaign Strategy"
    - First draft and related papers, 1995 (Box-folder 7/13)
    - Second draft, 1995 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Third draft, 1995 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Fourth draft, 1995 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Original copy of final draft, 1995 October (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Copy of final report, 1995 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Research notes, correspondence, etc., 1994-1995 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - "Various documents which may be needed for appendices", 1992-1995 (Box-folder 9/3)
- No on 36 campaign, 2004; Series E
  - Records and ephemera (Box-folder 9/4)
  - African American outreach and involvement (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Asian American, Latino, and Pacific Islander outreach and involement (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Endorser notes (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Lists (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Lobbying strategies and tips (Box-folder 9/9)
    Includes original folder that housed materials.
  - Plans (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Promotional materials and advertisements (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Post-election records (Box-folder 10/2)
- Other activism, 1991-1995; Series F
  - Notes and papers on activism and leadership workshops, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 10/3)
    Had been originally housed in a binder.
  - "Analysis and Response Plan to Traditional Values Coalition Videotape 'Gay Rights/Special Rights'" by Renée DeLapp, 1993 October 22 (Box-folder 10/4)
    Includes related papers.
  - "Campaign Messages and Audiences", 1995 (Box-folder 10/5)
    Chart designed by Pruett.
  - Community Strategic Training Initiative (CSTI) records, 1991 (Box-folder 10/6)
    Includes original folder with timelogs.
  - Easel sheets with notes from CSTI meeting, 1991 (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Federal Advocacy Network, 1994 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Human Rights Campaign Fund, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Papers re immigration and affirmative action, 1994-1995; undated (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Program for Mackenize River Gathering with piece on Rural Organizing Project's work on No on 9, 1994 (Box-folder 10/10)
  - Memo on draft plan for National Freedom to Marry Coalition, 1995 September 6 (Box-folder 10/11)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, "Action Kit - Fight the Right: March on Washington Edition", circa 1993 (Box-folder 10/12)
  - Non-Oregon materials, Subseries 1
    - Non-Oregon anti-gay groups, 1994 (Box-folder 10/13)
    - News releases re non-Oregon measures, 1994 (Box-folder 10/14)
    - Michigan Campaign for Human Dignity records, 1994 (Box-folder 10/15)
    - Washington Citizens for Fairness/Hands off Washington grant proposal, 1993 (Box-folder 10/16)
    - Washington Citizens for Fairness/Hands off Washington records, 1993 November (Box-folder 10/17)
      Had originally been housed with SOC PAC "Reading" folder.
    - Washington Citizens for Fairness records, 1994 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Oregon House Democratic Campaign Committee "Model Campaign Plan: 1992 Primary Election"
  - Oregon Speak Out Project, 1993 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Oregonian issue with article on cultural divide over gay rights, 1993 July 11 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Portland Police Bureau/Sexual Minorities Partnership Agreement, 1994 September-October (Box-folder 12/10)
  - E-Mail correspondence and photocopied clippings re Tom Potter's withdrawal from U.S. Justice Department nomination, 1994 October (Box-folder 11/4)
    Potter, then Portland police chief, withdrew after Potter's support of gay rights became considered controversial by the Clinton Administration.
  - Research on history of bigotry and discrimination, 1995 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - "The Right Response: A Report on National Gay and Lesbian Task Force 'Fight the Right' Activities in 1993", 1994 January (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Draft, "Run and Win Workbook," by Dave Fleischer, 1995 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Search Conference, 1991 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Western States Center, 1994 (Box-folder 11/9)
- Other papers and ephemera, 1969-1998; Series G
  - Brochure, "Black Studies at Reed", 1969 July (Box-folder 11/11)
  - Court order re Kennneth Lewis v. Phil Keisling, Scott Lively, et al., 1994 September 6 (Box-folder 11/12)
  - Event flyer with note on back, circa 1994 (Box-folder 11/13)
    Note reads, "Counties in OR by Cong. dist." Note was probably originally attached to a list.
  - Publications and articles, Subseries 1
    - Article "The Crisis of Socialism and the Third World," by Franz J. Hinkelammert, 1993 (Box-folder 11/14)
    - Gretchen: The Story of Gretchen Miller Kafoury, 1998 (Box-folder 11/15)
    - Issues of Just Out, 1994 November 4; 1995 November 17 (Box-folder 12/8)
    - Issue of The Lesbian Insider Insighter Inciter, 1981 January (Box-folder 11/16)
    - Issue of Transformation, 1994 January-February (Box-folder 11/17)
    - Article, "Rebuilding Politics from the Ground Up", 1993 (Box-folder 11/18)
    - Article, "Who Killed L.A.? The War Against the Cities," by Mike Davis, 1993 June (Box-folder 11/19)
  - Voters' pamphlet for May 1994 election (Box-folder 11/20)